Patrick K. Martin

Phone: (401) 595-8552 • E-Mail: pkmartin82@gmail.com • LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/pkmartin82



SUMMARY

As a software professional with over 13 years of technical and managerial experience, I have held key roles in multiple software disciplines. I have worked in all phases of the software development lifecycle and I have found my specialties in both microservice architectural design and leadership of business-critical teams.

EXPERIENCE

Director, Application Development

Tuition Management Systems

Sept. 2017 - Current

- Director of three IT departments: Quality Assurance, Production Support, Release Engineering
- Managing six direct and five indirect reports at multiple locations
- Proven success in building high-performing, multi-functional teams
- Championing DevOps and Continuous Improvement culture and values throughout organization
- Organizing Release Engineering duties for 80+ Java and .NET applications and 20+ VB6/COM+ applications
- Assuring application quality via manual and automated testing through Selenium Webdriver, Katalon, SQL
- Providing architectural input to development initiatives, specifically microservice design and function
- Coordinating and supporting job scheduling operations using Control-M Framework
- Leading initiative to convert from on-premises to Amazon Web Services (AWS) cloud strategy
- Converting Perforce and AnthillPro to AWS Code Commit (Git), Code Build, Deploy and Pipeline
- Incorporated IT Operations into Agile practices, like daily standups, sprint/release planning, retrospectives
- Reduced Post-Release defects by over 50% by instituting organization-wide regression testing effort
- Created a rapid triage, investigation and fix-deployment process used after major releases to production
- Revamped, automated and increased frequency of server patching process

Manager, Application Development

Tuition Management Systems

Oct. 2014 - Sept. 2017

- Manager of two IT departments: Quality Assurance and Production Support
- Managed nine direct reports at multiple locations, plus contract developers and outside consultants
- Introduced Selenium IDE and Webdriver Automated Frameworks to QA staff
- Increased agile stories verified automatically per sprint from 0% to 60% in 18 months
- Implemented priority-based system to triage and resolve production application support tickets
- Developed and executed escalation procedures to resolve Top priority issues
- Coordinated integration of a new microservice with outside vendor to add text messaging capabilities
- Interviewed and onboarded new employees / participated in employee turnover

Senior Software Developer

Tuition Management Systems

June 2012 - Oct. 2014

- Scrum Master and Lead Developer of a web application integrating TMS suite with remote client systems
- Lead Developer of a microservice integrating with Verizon's Interactive Voice Response (IVR) system.
- Client-facing IT representative in support-calls/marketing initiatives with both vendors and clients

Senior Software Engineer

Raytheon Co.

July 2005 - June 2012

- Designed, developed, tested and supported distributed system infrastructure-software for Zumwalt-class US Navy surface ships throughout all phases of the software development lifecycle
- Performed enterprise-level system integration testing of Zumwalt software with US Navy Technical Team
- Elected President of the Young Employee Support Network; coordinated events for new-hire acclimation

Patrick K. Martin

Phone: (401) 595-8552 • E-Mail: pkmartin82@gmail.com • LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/pkmartin82



EDUCATION

Master of Business Administration

University of Rhode Island

Fall 2009 – Summer 2011

• Beta Gamma Sigma Honor Society

- Cumulative GPA: 3.78
- Degree Focus in Computer Science

Bachelor of Science, Computer Engineering

- Cumulative GPA: 3.83, Summa Cum Laude
- Computer Engineering Salutatorian

University of Rhode Island

Fall 2000 - Spring 2004

- Minored in Mathematics
- Tau Beta Pi, Phi Eta Sigma Honor Societies

SKILLS

- Crisis management: ability to quickly, clearly and confidently handle adverse emergency situations
- Motivating and engaging people
- Relaying technical information to non-technical audiences
- Public speaking
- Certified as a Raytheon Six Sigma Specialist

TECHNOLOGIES

- Release Engineering technologies: Git, Perforce, AnthillPro, Maven, MSBuild, SourceSafe, custom-built tools
- Cloud technologies: GitHub, AWS: IAM, Code Commit, Code Build, Code Deploy, Code Pipeline
- Programming Languages: Java and .Net (C#), HTML, XML, SQL, JavaScript
- Automated Testing Platforms: JUnit, Selenium IDE (retired) and Webdriver, Katalon Recorder and Studio
- Server Platforms: Experience developing in, configuring and supporting JBoss EAP, Microsoft IIS, Tomcat
- Server Patching Technologies: Ivanti (Windows), Satellite (Red Hat Enterprise Linux)
- Project / Defect Management Tools: Jira, Confluence, Crucible, Incident Monitor
- Microsoft Office suite
- Operating Systems: Windows, Windows Server, Linux, MacOS

ABOUT ME

For the past 25 years, I have been an avid comic book collector. My primary collection is Amazing Spider-Man, having over 720 of the 800+ issues in the series. To date, the oldest comic book I own is from 1965, but my most prized issue is relatively new. In 2015 my son and I had our picture printed in an issue, and later had that issue signed by the late, great Stan Lee, the co-creator of Spider-Man and the entire Marvel Universe. On family vacations, we like to visit local comic book stores, hoping to "fill the gaps" in my collection. It is a fun hobby to share with my family!